# 哈喽大家好
Hello, everyone!
# 过两天就快要到端午节了
The Dragon Boat Festival is coming soon.
# 今天跟我四伯爷还有我的亲戚送点这个粽子
I will send some zongzis to my uncle and my relatives.
# 这个是我自己定的粽子
I bought them myself.
# 就是这种礼盒装的一盒是6个
They are gift-wrapped and each box has 6 zongzis.
# 拿4份去送
I will bring 4 boxes with me.
# 然后还有一箱这个凉糕
There is a box of lianggao (sweet rice cake).
# 一箱凉糕是30多盒就是1件
More than 30 packs in one box.
# 然后我妈买了一些土鸡蛋给我外婆拿去
And my mother bought some free-range eggs for my grandma.
# 这个是啥子哦
What is it?
# 这是李子嘎
These are plums.
# 嗯
Ok.
# 还摘了一些李子
And we picked some plums.
# 还有一些香蕉
Some bananas then.
# 今天休息一下去看我外婆
Take today off to visit my grandma.
# 自驾游
A road trip.
# 走嘛 上车
Let’s go. Get in.
# 空调你不要指到吹撒
Don't face the airflow directly.
# 指到吹一会儿你头要痛
Or you will get a headache.
# 诶呀 都撒尿了
It's peeing.
# 别动
Stay!
# 脖子上毛都磨掉了
The fur around the neck is worn off.
# 别动
Stay!
# 好乖哦
How clever!
# 这狗特别的热情
It’s very friendly.
# 这狗的年纪比我儿子还大一个月
It’s one month older than my son.
# 比你的孙子都还大一个月
One month older than your grandson.
# 现在有半岁了
It’s 6 months old.
# 四伯爷
Uncle.
# 又遭了哦可能又要封场（赶集）了哦
Have to go to the market again.
# 我给你拿了口罩来
I brought you some masks.
# 今天我在街上听到说
I heard on the street
# 他们拿回来的冻肉都不准卖了
that frozen meat is no longer allowed for sale
# 这街上
On the street.
# 口罩现在也比较难买只拿到10个给你
I only brought you 10 masks because the supply is running low.
# 要得
Ok.
# 你赶场的时候人多你就戴起
Put it on if it's crowded when you go to the market.
# 好嘛 好
Ok.
# 反正你赶场没得问题的
It should be fine for you to go to the market.
# 给你拿一盒粽子来
A box of zongzis for you.
# 哎呀
Aw.
# 还有凉糕呢
And some lianggao.
# 又拿粽子来
You brought zongzis again.
# 拿这么多凉糕来
And so much lianggao.
# 放在冰箱里冻了再吃
Eat them after they are cooled down in the fridge.
# 放在保鲜室都嘛
Put in the refrigerator compartment.
# 嗯 保鲜室
Yes. Refrigerator compartment.
# 我帮你吃一盒嘛
I will help you to eat one.
# 伯娘呢
Where is aunt?
# 吃凉糕伯娘
Aunt, have some lianggao.
# 一会儿我还要给舅婆他们提一些去
I’m going to send some to Jiupo (Wang Gang's grandma's sister in law) later.
# 她在屋头撒
She is at home?
# 在屋头 还是带这些东西啊
At home. You're bringing the same stuff?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 给她拿粽子跟凉糕
I'll bring some zongzis and lianggao.
# 明天我要出去学习
I will go on a study trip tomorrow.
# 走哪里嘛 走杭州啊
Where? Hangzhou?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 出去还是把口罩戴好
Well, wear a mask when you go out.
# 必须的撒
Of course.
# 要得四伯爷你慢慢吃
Take your time to eat. Uncle.
# 我送下一家 我走了哈
I’m leaving for the next stop.
# 好
Ok.
# 狗儿就不去了撒 你要跟着去啊
Doggie, you stay. You want to go with me?
# 等它去啊
Let’s go.
# 那走嘛
Go.
# 舅公
Jiugong (Wang Gang's grandma's brother).
# 幺舅你还在宰鱼啊
Still butchering fish, uncle?
# 给你拿点粽子还有凉糕
I've brought you some zongzis and lianggao.
# 你在这边吃饭噶
Why don't you stay and have lunch with us?
# 不坐 我们一会儿就要走
We won't stay for long. We are leaving soon.
# 坐会儿撒 坐会儿多
Have a seat and stay for a while.
# 吃西瓜
Have some watermelon.
# 不坐了
No need to sit.
# 你拿西瓜来切哈我去宰完了来
Cut some watermelon for them and I will come back after I'm done with the fish.
# 我舅公他们是养鱼的
My Jiugong and his wife are fish farmers.
# 专门在这里喂鱼你看这里全是鱼饲料
All of these are fish feed.
# 他多的时候仓库里面
Sometimes,
# 几十吨的这个鱼饲料
there are literally tons of fish feed in the warehouse.
# 他一买都是买几十吨
He buys tens of tons every time.
# 这里几口鱼塘全是他们的
They own several fish ponds.
# 现在鲢鱼还小要给它宰一下
The silver carp is small. I'll butcher it.
# 你多久都没下来吃鱼了你不下来吃鱼了啊
We haven't seen you in a while! Aren't you gonna stay and have fish with us?
# 下次嘛
Next time.
# 下次
# 要得我就先回去了嘛我还要看外婆
I'm leaving now if that's okay. I have to visit my grandma.
# 舅婆我就先走了哦
Jiupo, I’m leaving.
# 你外婆现在在哪里哦
Where is your grandmother live?
# 在我舅舅那里
She's living with my uncle (Wang Gang's mother's brother)
# 我去看哈我外婆
I’m going to see my grandma.
# 这块（西瓜）给娃娃带回去嘛
Take this to the kid.
# 不拿
Nah we're good.
# 这个是老家种的嘛你再买得多都没有这个好撒
This is homegrown, better than those sold at the market.
# 拿去
Take it.
# 我们走了舅婆
Jiupo, we are leaving.
# 真的不拿
No need.
# 好啦 现在到我外婆家了
Ok. We are arriving at my grandma’s home.
# 提点粽子
I've brought some zongzis.
# 我外婆虽然牙口不好吃这个粽子还是吃得了的
Although she has weak teeth, she can eat zongzi.
# 然后拿了点凉糕
Also some lianggao.
# 还有鸡蛋
And eggs.
# 青菜跟西瓜
Vegetables and watermelon.
# 外婆
Grandma.
# 我给你拿点粽子
I've brought you some zongzis.
# 这个凉糕我知道你牙齿不好给你拿了几盒凉糕
I know you have difficulty chewing so I brought you some lianggao.
# 我头发都没梳钢夹也没扎你给我照的相像什么样啊
I didn't brush or tie up my hair. I'm not camera-ready.
# 人家都说你长得很漂亮
People say you are beautiful.
# 我还漂亮啊
I’m beautiful?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 老都老了还漂亮
Too old to be beautiful.
# 不老啊 你心态不老都嘛
Not old. You have a young mindset.
# 人老心不老花有几样红
Old physically but young mentally. Each flower has its own beauty.
# 哦对头
Yes!
# 哈哈哈
Hahaha.
# 买些这些东西来
You bought too many things.
# 不是买的这个你外孙自己做的
It’s made by your grandson. Not bought.
# 这是我们厂里自己做的不是买的
It’s made by our own food factory. Not bought.
# 在外面都是5块钱1盒
Similar products cost 5 yuan per box.
# 我们这个才卖3块钱1盒
Ours cost only 3 yuan per box.
# 里面有糖啊
Is there some sugar inside?
# 一会儿我给你放嘛
I will put some in for you later.
# 你钢夹呢拿来别到
Where is your hair clip? I'll put your hair up.
# 在屋里你去给我拿嘛
In the room, can you bring it to me?
# 以前我都弄这些来卖过
I have made and sold these before.
# 我都卖过这起的我自己弄
Homemade and sold.
# 自己拿米来泡起自己磨的
I soaked and ground the rice by myself.
# 我给你压得来不哦
Let me put it in your hair.
# 吃嘛 吃凉糕
Come on. Have some lianggao.
# 人家要笑我 我不吃
No. People will laugh at me.
# 没得人笑你的
Nobody laughs at you.
# 你看到他就想笑你啊
You thought he's laughing at you?
# 我这么脏一个人照起像什么嘛
I’m a mess. Why are you filming me?
# 哪里嘛大家都说你长得很美
Everyone thinks you are beautiful.
# 我还美啊
I’m beautiful!?
# 以前是个美女
You were a beauty.
# 你年轻的时候是个大美女
When you young, you were a gorgeous beautiful woman.
# 都晓得
Everyone knows.
# 难怪以前你外公那么稀奇我哦
No wonder your grandfather loved me so much.
# 在我脸上摸一把
（One of my friends）once touched my face.
# 我说你摸我做什么
I said: "What was that for?"
# 她说我打了粉的结果没得
She said she wanted to see if I was wearing makeup. And I wasn't.
# 难怪得你二哥那么爱你哦
“No wonder your husband loves you so much.”
# 硬是粉白粉白的
My skin was peachy and bright.
# 外婆你就在屋头你自己整来吃
Grandma, you can reheat it (zongzi) yourself.
# （粽子）蒸一哈就可以吃了
Just steam it for a while.
# 这个打开也可以吃
This one is ready-to-eat.
# 这个一会儿放在冰箱里面
Put this in the fridge later.
# 冻哈更好吃
It tastes better when it's cold.
# 放在冰箱里就是
Put it in fridge.
# 然后我们下次再来看你哈
We will visit you again soon.
# 西瓜你口干了就拿来吃
When you are thirsty, have some watermelon.
# 鸡蛋也可以煮
You can cook the eggs too.
# 要得外婆我们就先回去了
Grandma, we are leaving.
# 要得 麻烦了你们哦
Okay. Thank you for your trouble.
# 外婆你说这些咋子 我都是你带大的
Don’t say that. You are the one who brought me up.
# 给我拿这么多东西来我又要吃好久嘛
You brought me so much stuff. It'll take me a long time to finish.
# 慢慢吃
Take your time.
# 好我们先走了
We are leaving.
# 不送不送
Don’t see us off.
# 你坐到就是
No need to get up.
# 我都要出去耍了
I’m going out anyway.
# 要得
Ok.
# 晓得嘛 打会儿麻将嘛
I know. I'm going to play mahjong.
# 下次过端午早点过来陪你打麻将
For next year's Dragon Boat Festival, we'll come here earlier to play mahjong with you.
# 我外婆特别喜欢打麻将
My grandma likes playing mahjong very much.
# 过端午就陪你打麻将
I'll play mahjong with you on next Dragon Boat Festival.
# 要得 你们慢慢走
Good. Take care.
# 好 拜拜
Bye bye.
# 要得你回去坐到嘛
You go back to sit.
# 你们先走嘛
You go first.